<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>enterpreneur</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.rahulsrajan.com/tag/enterpreneur/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 17:57:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.5</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/cropped-IMG_20150920_161044-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>enterpreneur</title>
	<link>https://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Entrepreneurs , Devils in disguise</title>
		<link>https://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/07/16/entrepreneurs-devils-in-disguise/</link>
		<comments>https://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/07/16/entrepreneurs-devils-in-disguise/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 06:08:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rahul S Rajan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lifestyle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[enterpreneur]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://minimalistsconfessions.wordpress.com/?p=575</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Entrepreneurs make our world a better place to live in. They are problem solvers. But its the way they create and solve our problems, that makes them Devils in Disguise.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1851" src="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/devil-in-disguise.jpg" alt="devil-in-disguise" width="698" height="400" srcset="https://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/devil-in-disguise.jpg 698w, https://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/devil-in-disguise-300x172.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 698px) 100vw, 698px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">In order for a company to be successful, its products have to solve a problem faced by the customers. The person who understands that problem, and finds a solution to it, is often called an Entrepreneur. They make our lives easier.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Imagine the world without entrepreneurs. we would have no Cell phone, no Internet, no Facebook, no eharmony, no Tinder. One can say that they have made the world a better place for us mortals to live in, but often times money is the big motivator. I’m not saying its bad, they should be rewarded for their efforts, for they have created value for other people.<span id="more-575"></span></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">‘Entrepreneurs must have one key skill, They must be an expert on Human Unhappiness.’</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
Today there are products to fill every aspect of our lives, Not looking good? try some beauty products from the world&#8217;s leading brands, Can&#8217;t find a date? look up at the countless dating sites and services. Not content with your life? join a spirituality course to rejuvenate yourself. Every aspect you can think of there are companies there to provide you with their products which can make the job easier for you.Money being the big motivator, in a Capitalistic society<em>, science, and technology will only progress in the direction which is profitable.</em> That means more consumer technologies, and less attention is given to sustainable developments because making the world a better place to live in is bad for business.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: justify;">So is it bad?</h4>
<p style="text-align: justify;">They are making our lives easier right? true, But my only worry is, Are they making our lives too easy? we now have the capacity to outsource anything. we don’t have to do the hard work of figuring it out ourselves, we can pay someone to do it for us.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Hence we will not value an individual’s intelligence anymore, why should we? when we can pay someone else to do it for us. So the only commodity we consumers value would be money.  A person&#8217;s worth will be measured by the amount of money he or she has, because with it, he can buy any service he wants.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Don’t get me wrong, I’m not painting a bad picture for Entrepreneurs. I’m speaking about the rest of the world who are consumers and have grown to be dependent on these technologies. Little do they know about the luxuries they have, and the amount of work gone into making them. And with this comes a sense of Entitlement, like the world owes them these luxuries.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But all is not bad, though we have become a lazy, judgemental, emotionless society we now have the ability to make other people do the work for us. Which is good right?</p>
<h4 style="text-align: justify;">So how come they are devils?</h4>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Entrepreneurs are people like us and most of them are good people but they have a devil’s mind in the sense that, in order for them to sell you a product, you must have a problem that needs solving, and if no genuine problems exist, They will create a problem (need), and sell you the solution.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">This is what the beauty industry is focused on, to highlight your physical flaws, and sell you a solution. The same as how Airline companies use our inconvenience to make us pay more ( your inconvenience about the boarding and economy seats is used to make you pay more to avoid this hassle and get a business upgrade). As said earlier, an <strong>Entrepreneur must be an expert on Human unhappiness</strong>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">THE WORLD</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The World is increasingly designed to depress us. Happiness isn&#8217;t very good for the economy. If we were happy with what we had, why would we need more? How do you sell an anti-ageing moisturiser? You make someone worry about ageing. How do you get people to vote for a political party? You make them worry about immigration. How do you get them to buy insurance? By making them worry about everything. How do you get them to have plastic surgery? By highlighting their phys-ical flaws. How do you get them to watch a TV show? By making them worry about missing out. How do you get them to buy a new smartphone? By making them feel like they are being left behind. To be calm becomes a kind of revolutionary act. To be happy with your own non-upgraded existence. To be comfortable with our messy, human selves, would not be good for business.  &#8211; Anonymus</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Paints a sorry picture doesn&#8217;t it? But we are far too busy to notice this, looking into our new iPhone 6s, posting selfies on Instagram.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We are being herded like sheep by the wolves that run Multinational corporations. They have an extensive knowledge of our psychology and are willing to use them against us.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">It&#8217;s up to you, Do you want to remain a sheep and follow the Herd? Or do you want to wake up, stand on your own feet and learn to think for yourselves?</p>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: justify;">NOTE</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">If you want to know more about the &#8216;Psychology of persuasion&#8217;.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Read &#8216;<strong>Ínfluence</strong>&#8216;by <strong>Robert B Cialdini</strong>.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">It&#8217;s a classic and great source of information, His book is one of the best and explains how markets influence us to buy products, in a simple easy to understand way.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">You can connect with me on <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/rahulrajanofficial">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.s.rajan1">Facebook</a>,  and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/rahul.rajan1/">Instagram</a>. I hope to meet new people and tell more stories</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>https://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/07/16/entrepreneurs-devils-in-disguise/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
