<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Modern day zombies</title>
	<atom:link href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/tag/modern-day-zombies/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 06:11:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/cropped-IMG_20150920_161044-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Modern day zombies</title>
	<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Modern Day Zombie Apocalypse</title>
		<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/25/the-modern-day-zombie-apocalypse/</link>
		<comments>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/25/the-modern-day-zombie-apocalypse/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 15:53:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rahul S Rajan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lifestyle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Apocalypse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mobile phones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Modern day zombies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zombies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://minimalistsconfessions.wordpress.com/?p=95</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>It's not the flesh eating monsters we hoped, but a more insidious one. Invisible yet Omnipresent.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/25/the-modern-day-zombie-apocalypse/">The Modern Day Zombie Apocalypse</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-194" src="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/3f26d9aca50b61c4f767df77b8706d951.jpg" alt="3f26d9aca50b61c4f767df77b8706d95" width="736" height="376" srcset="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/3f26d9aca50b61c4f767df77b8706d951.jpg 736w, http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/3f26d9aca50b61c4f767df77b8706d951-300x153.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 736px) 100vw, 736px" />A zombie is a person who is or appears lifeless, apathetic, or completely unresponsive to their surroundings. Sounds familiar right and they don&#8217;t just exist in the movies anymore. we see them everywhere, trains, colleges, coffee shops. And sadly for gamers and movie fanatics alike, the modern-day zombie invasion is much more insidious than one might imagine. There are less running and screaming and you don&#8217;t have to sacrifice your fat friend to escape, just a suggestion though.<span id="more-95"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">we live in a world where technology impacts every part of our lives, from communication to Fitness, we have given control of many of our daily activities over to technology,  it has replaced the need for physical or mental exertion. Our technology gets us off our beds, tells us how far we walked, and how far we have to walk in order to burn than pizza we just ate. My point is this, consumer technologies that are designed to help automate our lives are taking away our mental capacity. They are designed for the layman, you don&#8217;t have to think to use them; you know how  we used to drive cars with Manual transmissions, flash forward, we now have smart cars, Driver-less cars. It takes skill to drive a manual, a skill which has been replaced by driver aids, We are dumbing down the human race.</p>
<blockquote class="alignleft"><p>Use technology like Medication, not as vitamins.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Remember the old days when we remembered our friends birthdays and phone numbers, well those days have passed, and are now replaced by Instant Messaging and Social Media, where we live pseudo lives trying to impress random people and keeping up a pseudo social image. How we have degraded the necessity of the human connections. we spend so much of our waking hours online, we rarely get to live our lives anymore. It&#8217;s like dangling a carrot in front of the donkey, It doesn&#8217;t see anything else, cursed to ever walk towards the unattainable goal.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The saddest part for me is how we have degraded the value of a simple Photograph. I&#8217;m a Photographer and I enjoy the finer details in one, the story, the lighting, the composition. A Photograph used to mean so much back then, It&#8217;s a slice of time we get to keep, a memory, a simple thing to look back on some day. And to think that this, which used to hold much value then, to be replaced by despicable Duck faces and Boob selfies. It saddens me to the core.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Epigenetics, the study of how external factors affect our genes, tells us that we are affecting the way our cells read our genes. we are leaving behind a legacy of self-destruction and isolation for our kids.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Not to mention how our social and Moral values have shifted, Festivals and family hangouts which used to represent the importance human connections and social values, now become an isolated and distracted place. We do not see, what we have become.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-174" src="https://minimalistsconfessions.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/albert.jpg" alt="albert" width="500" height="305" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Image Source: Google</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">You see people being herded like sheep, people incessantly posting selfies to get attention. People being bombarded with information, which prevents them from thinking. We must strive to be better than that. we must become creators, not consumers, and for the few who can, we must show them a better way to live.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Carpe diem, Seize the day!.</p>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: justify;">You can connect with me on <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/rahulrajanofficial">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/rahul.s.rajan1">Facebook</a>,  and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/rahul.rajan1/">Instagram</a>. I hope to meet new people and tell more stories</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/25/the-modern-day-zombie-apocalypse/">The Modern Day Zombie Apocalypse</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/25/the-modern-day-zombie-apocalypse/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
