<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Education</title>
	<atom:link href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/category/education/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 06:11:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/cropped-IMG_20150920_161044-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Education</title>
	<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The 7 Steps to starting your own business from scratch</title>
		<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/</link>
		<comments>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 17:19:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rahul S Rajan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How to start a business]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.rahulsrajan.com/?p=2736</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Starting your own business is a dream for many, yet it doesn’t have to be. Let’s take a look at some of the things you need to do in your journey to becoming an entrepreneur. Step one: Picking a Niche market. Before you set out to begin any venture, you must first understand who your ... <span class="more"><a class="more-link" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/">[Read more...]</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/">The 7 Steps to starting your own business from scratch</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Starting your own business is a dream for many, yet it doesn’t have to be. Let’s take a look at some of the things you need to do in your journey to becoming an entrepreneur.</p>
<h2><strong>Step one: Picking a Niche market.</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-168 alignleft" src="https://i2.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/pexels-photo-1.jpg?resize=700%2C692" alt="set up your Niche Market" width="216" height="213" /></p>
<p>Before you set out to begin any venture, you must first understand who your customers are and what exactly is it that they need?<b> It is very hard to create demand, but relatively easy to fill a demand.</b> Don’t create a product/service and start searching for people to sell it to. Find a market—define your customers—then develop a product for them. It is done best when you, yourself are a member of the target market. Don’t speculate what others need or are willing to buy.</p>
<blockquote><p>“<em>It is said that if everyone’s your customer, then no one is your customer</em>”</p></blockquote>
<p><span id="more-2736"></span></p>
<p><strong>All product or service ideas emerge out of problems</strong>, problems faced by ordinary people in their daily life. Facebook was developed as a way for people to stay in touch and share their social lives, Instagram was developed as a way for people to share their photos online easily. Whatsapp was developed as a platform that helped people keep in touch with messages. In the core of all these businesses lies a problem that needed solving.</p>
<p><strong>The size of the problem you solve</strong> <strong>will determine the growth of your company.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;All entrepreneurs must have one key skill, they must be an expert on human unhappiness&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>An entrepreneur must answer many questions like,</p>
<ul>
<li>Who are the target audience?</li>
<li>How do you intend to reach them?</li>
<li>Who are the competitors to your business?</li>
<li>How can you differentiate yourself from them?</li>
</ul>
<p>By preparing answers for these beforehand, you will come across as confident and a trustworthy business owner in the eyes of the investors. This will be the hardest part of the journey, but it is also the most crucial step. A strong foundation paves the way for building up your business.</p>
<h2><strong>Step two: Decide the Business Structure/plan.</strong></h2>
<p><strong><img class="wp-image-171 alignright" src="https://i1.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/pexels-photo-95916.jpeg?resize=700%2C466" alt="Business strategy" width="264" height="176" />         </strong>The main parts of a business plan include <strong>a company description</strong>, <strong>a market analysis</strong> (the competition and target demographics), the <strong>company’s structure</strong>, a description of the service or product line, the marketing and sales strategy, financial projections.</p>
<p>Each firm is different and will have business plans unique to their environment. A strong business plan lays the guidelines on working procedures within the company.</p>
<h3>A Business Model Canvas</h3>
<p><strong>Alex Osterwalder</strong>, a Swiss business theorist defines the nine key building blocks of our business model as:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Customer Segments</strong> &#8211; The groups of people and organizations a company or organization aims to reach and create value for.</li>
<li><strong>Value Proposition</strong> &#8211; The bundle of products and services that create value for a Customer Segment.</li>
<li><strong>Channels</strong> &#8211; Describe how a Value Proposition is communicated and delivered to a Customer Segment through communication, distribution, and sales channels.</li>
<li><strong>Customer Relationships</strong> &#8211; Outline what type of relationship is established and maintained with each Customer Segment, and explain how customers are acquired and retained.</li>
<li><strong>Revenue Streams</strong> &#8211; Result from a Value Proposition successfully offered to a Customer Segment. It is how an organization captures value at a price that customers are willing to pay.</li>
<li><strong>Key Resources</strong> &#8211; Are the most important assets required to offer and deliver the previously described elements.</li>
<li><strong>Key Activitie</strong>s &#8211; Are the most important activities an organization needs to perform well.</li>
<li><strong>Key Partnerships</strong> &#8211; Show the network of suppliers and partners that bring in external resources and activities.</li>
<li><strong>Cost Structure</strong> &#8211; Describes all costs incurred to operate a business model.</li>
</ol>
<p>This will give you an outline on what all is required in your business model.</p>
<p>When you are a startup, don&#8217;t spend much time on making a business plan. Your business will evolve as it develops and so will your business plan.</p>
<ul>
<li>Nokia started out as a paper mill.</li>
<li>Sony started out selling radios.</li>
<li>Ducati started out by making electronics.</li>
</ul>
<p>Don&#8217;t fall into the trap of envisioning an all-encompassing business plan that can cover all possible outcomes. Start out with by deciding a company structure and flesh out plans that are required at in the present or the near future, and develop it as you mature.</p>
<h2><strong>Step three: Register you company.</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-172 alignleft" src="https://i1.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/pexels-photo-2-1.jpg?resize=700%2C466" alt="Register your company" width="254" height="169" /></p>
<p>Once you have decided on your product/services, and have made a business plan, It&#8217;s time to register your startup. You will need a company name and a logo for registration. Decide whether you want to register your startup as a Proprietorship firm/Partnership Firm/ LLP / Private Limited Company / One Person Company.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>The 5 types of companies that can be registered in India</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sole Proprietorship Company</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>This is the easiest way to start a business in India. When the business is owned and managed by a single person Sole Proprietorship Company may be formed. A business can be up and running in this format within 15 days</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Partnership Firm</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>           </strong>A General Partnership is a business structure in which two or more individuals manage and operate a business in accordance with the terms and objectives set out in the Partnership Deed.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>One Person Company</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>One Person Company is the improvement over Sole Proprietorship firm which gives complete control to one founder and gives a benefit of Limited Liability to the founder.OPC is registered with Registrar of Companies (RoC) under Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA)</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Limited Liability Partnership</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>LLP is a significant improvement on Partnership firms, which give Limited Liability to the Partners involved and also it has lesser compliances compared to a Pvt Ltd Company since the working of an LLP is solely dependent on the Partnership deed that is drafted between the partners and is filed with RoC.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Private Limited Company</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Private Limited Companies are the <strong>most preferred option</strong> for any startup that is looking at scaling up by external funding as it is very easy in Private Limited Company to issue fresh equity shares in lieu of funding received.</p>
<p>Each one should be considered as a different legal entity and they have different requirement for qualification. Your choice should depend on the future goal you have in mind.</p>
<p>In order to cover all the legal aspects, such as intellectual property and patents, it is best advised to consult a startup lawyer before you go ahead with the registration.</p>
<h2><strong>Step four: Get your finances in order.</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-173 alignright" src="https://i1.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/business-money-pink-coins.jpg?resize=700%2C458" alt="Get your finances in order" width="249" height="162" /></p>
<p>Once you have your company or proprietorship registered, open a corporate account with a bank.<strong>It is advised not to conduct business with a personal account</strong> as it may cause problems at a later stage. There are many ways you can get funding for your startup, which includes,</p>
<ul>
<li>raising capital from friends/co-founders</li>
<li>finding angel investors</li>
<li>taking a loan from banks</li>
</ul>
<p>When starting out, <strong>getting recurring revenue should be your first priority</strong>. Startups usually have a limited pool of resources to dip into. In order for the business to stay afloat, getting revenue should be at the core of all your tasks,</p>
<blockquote><p><em>you have to survive long </em>enough<em> in the race to win it. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>With revenue as your primary focus, you can develop your product with the resources you are now generating. This will ensure that your company will survive in the long run.</p>
<h2><strong>Step five: Set up your digital space.</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-174 alignleft" src="https://i2.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/startup-photos-1.jpg?resize=700%2C466" alt="Set up your digital space" width="280" height="186" /></p>
<p>We are no longer bound by the limits of the traditional businesses, in this technology-laden world, the majority of people get their information online hence we must develop our footprint in the digital space. It can be as simple as a one-page website with details about your product/services and contact information.</p>
<p>There are many platforms where you can start your website. Some are free and others are not.</p>
<p>The first thing I recommend —when starting out— is to <strong>open a Facebook page</strong> for your proposed business. It&#8217;s relatively easy and helps to market validate your product. You can even start selling on Facebook by opening a Facebook store. And depending on the feedback you receive from your customers, you can proceed to set up an independent website or try some other platform.</p>
<p>Many online platforms that help you set up a website include <strong><a href="https://www.strikingly.com/">Strikingly</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.squarespace.com/">Squarespace</a></strong>, <strong><a href="http://unbounce.com/">Unbounce</a></strong> and most definitely <strong><a href="http://www.wordpress.com/">WordPress</a></strong>. These platforms are great places to start. And you definitely don&#8217;t need any coding skills to start your website, trust me, I&#8217;m a Mechanical Engineer.</p>
<p>WordPress is by far the easiest to learn and deploy, It&#8217;s free if you want to try it out, and as your business grows, you can move to a dedicated site.</p>
<p><strong>Important Note</strong>: There is one major problem with all the free platforms, like Facebook. <strong>It&#8217;s that you don&#8217;t own anything</strong>. You can be shut down if you don&#8217;t follow their guidelines. FB can change their policy one day and you can be left in the dust. I suggest, when your business picks up, you move to your own independent website, you can keep using Facebook, but just don&#8217;t rely on it heavily.</p>
<h2><strong>Step Six: Finding mentors and experienced people</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-175 alignright" src="https://i2.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/people-woman-coffee-meeting.jpg?resize=700%2C466" alt="Finding Mentors" width="247" height="164" /></p>
<p>Mentors are people who have accomplished what you want to do. Their knowledge and experience will be invaluable in your journey. This is the step where you should consider becoming a part of a business accelerator. With their help, you will have access to many experienced people who can guide your journey.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.linkedin.com/"><strong>LinkedIn</strong></a> has emerged as the top platform for connecting with professionals from around the globe. Every aspiring professional must have his LinkedIn profile setup. It is a powerful platform for finding and connecting with people in your area of work.</p>
<h2><strong>Step seven: Attend Trade shows and Industry related events   </strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-176 alignleft" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.wbip.in/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/people-show-chairs-gym.jpg?resize=700%2C466" alt="Attending Trade shows" width="297" height="198" /></p>
<p>Attending trade shows and public events are a good way to meet up with like-minded people, who can help you. There comes a time when you have to stop working on your laptop and go out and Network with people. Most of these people would have already gone through the different phases your company is going through, they might also know more about the market you are targeting, hence their experiences are invaluable.</p>
<p><strong>Founders help other founders</strong>, so network with people in your line of work and share knowledge. I know this is hard, I find it very difficult to find and reach out to new people, but it&#8217;s an awesome feeling talking to other people like you, see they understand the pain you are going through.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Bonus: Skills that will come in handy</h2>
<h3>1. Copy Writing</h3>
<p>No matter what kind of business you are planning to start, writing is a skill you need to develop, be it writing business plans, writing a sales copy, or contacting prospective clients, people judge you through your writing. <strong>Professional writing is a skill you can take to any aspect of your life.</strong> Consider working on it. I&#8217;ve written an article to help you learn more about improving your writing, do check it out, <a href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/10/24/ways-to-improve-your-writing/">Weaving with words</a>.</p>
<h3>2. Digital Marketing</h3>
<p>The world has gone digital and so should your business, a good grasp of digital marketing fundamentals will guide you in acquiring new customers and retaining old ones. <strong>Marketing is the act of getting people who know nothing about your company to know more about it and how it can help them</strong>. No matter how good your product is, if no one knows about it or buys it, it will fail.</p>
<p>Digital Marketing is a huge domain, here are some of the things you need to focus on mainly,</p>
<ol>
<li>Search Engine optimization (SEO)</li>
<li>Social Media marketing</li>
<li>Content marketing</li>
</ol>
<p>If I must prioritize, I would give precedence to Search Engine Optimisation, this is how most people find you through search engines like Google, SEO must be at the core of your marketing strategy, it a long-term strategy that will bring you traffic for years to come.</p>
<h3>3. Accounting</h3>
<p>Whether you are an entrepreneur or business owner, learning to read numbers will be an invaluable skill to have. It gives you a clear picture of how your business is doing. <em>You cannot improve </em>anything<em> you cannot measure, </em>accounting gives you that ability to measure your financial progress.</p>
<h2>Final Notes</h2>
<p>Aspiring to become an entrepreneur is a noble quest, the world needs more problem solvers. Whether you are solving a problem in your community or changing the world, we stand united in our efforts. This journey is about a lot more than creating a company.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;Entrepreneurship is a management style that involves pursuing opportunities without regard to the resources currently controlled.&#8221;         —Howard Stevenson, Harvard University</p></blockquote>
<p>With that I bid you farewell, may you be successful in your quest.</p>
<hr />
<p>Find more stories on my <a href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/blog/">Blog</a></p>
<p>Find me on <a href="http://facebook.com/meetrahulrajan">Facebook</a>, <a href="http://www.instagram.com/ra.hul.rajan/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://in.linkedin.com/in/rahulsrajan">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/">The 7 Steps to starting your own business from scratch</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2017/01/11/7-steps-starting-business/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>College Graduates and Educated lions</title>
		<link>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/05/educated-lions/</link>
		<comments>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/05/educated-lions/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 11:34:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rahul S Rajan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College Graduates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://minimalistsconfessions.wordpress.com/2016/05/05/first-blog-post/</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>How the Lions of the Concrete Jungle compare with the wild ones.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/05/educated-lions/">College Graduates and Educated lions</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-88" src="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/download.png" alt="download" width="700" height="288" srcset="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/download.png 700w, http://www.rahulsrajan.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/download-300x123.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 700px) 100vw, 700px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Recently I read about a captive lion reintroduction program called &#8216;Walking with Lions&#8217;. The project focuses on releasing captive born African lions into the wild after supposedly training them to adapt to their natural setting. They have a system where the release is conducted in phases like reintroduction, rehabilitation etc.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">It sounds good on paper, but in reality it is not practical. The more we intervene with the way of life of these animals the more we destroy their natural instincts. These centers are Advertised as &#8216;wildlife encounters&#8217; programs and typically charge tourists and paying volunteers to pet, feed and walk with hand-raised and so-called tame lions.<span id="more-28"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The word &#8216;Educated&#8217; in this context describes a &#8216;Trained&#8217; Lion. The way humans want them. we have a similar situation happening in our everyday lives, our children.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The way we treat our children is similar to the way we treat lions, we try to control them, tell them what to do, follow what is told without question. These might work for toddlers but imagine as a kid spending his first twenty years of his life in a system like this, he has lost most of his natural gifts and is now nothing more than a person who does what is being told.</p>
<blockquote class="alignleft"><p>&#8220;The greatest Irony in our education system is that kids are taught to obey orders,  and when they graduate, they are expected to be free thinkers, creating their own paths in life.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The most difficult time arises when they comes out of the system and starts interacting with the real world, like finding a job. Similar to the way lion cubs behave when released to the wild after being born in captivity, they wait for someone to tell them what to do. All their life they have been taught to obey orders. But now there is no one to give them an order, they have to find their own way.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">It&#8217;s striking how most of  the successful people in the world are self-made men. They did not rely on any system to show them the path. They made their own. &#8220;They are the Lions of the Concrete Jungle&#8221;. They did not succumb to the common notion of education. They were the rebels, and now millions of people who followed the system depend on these rebel for their living.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Let us rise above this common notion of education and learn to think for ourselves, let us not disparage our children&#8217;s efforts nor point them away from their dreams. Let us come together and set them free. For no way is the right way, every way is different for each person.</p>
<blockquote>
<div>Two roads diverged in a wood, and I—</div>
<div>I took the one less traveled by,</div>
<div>And that has made all the difference.</div>
<div>                                              -Robert Frost</div>
</blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/05/educated-lions/">College Graduates and Educated lions</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.rahulsrajan.com"></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.rahulsrajan.com/2016/05/05/educated-lions/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
